<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="Constrained_Optimization_Methods_PR4"
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace" version="5">
	<title>Constrained Optimization Methods — Project 4</title>
	<para>As Dr. Mohamed El-Sayed shows in <xref
		linkend="pr_4_screenshot_assignment"/>, the assignment is to use the
		constrained optimization program developed in
		<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="Constrained_Optimization_Methods_PR3"/> 
		to solve example 5-1 of <olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="GNVNOTED"/>.
		We are also to compare our results with those in the book's tables 5-3
		through 5-5 and provide the iteration history printout of our solution.</para>
	<para>In addition to solving example 5-1, I have solved a more general
		problem: that of allowing distortion energy theory to control the design
		of the beam rather than just a maximum axial stress theory. Let's begin.</para>
	<figure xml:id="pr_4_screenshot_assignment">
		<title>Project 4 Assignment</title>
		<screenshot>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata fileref="mout/pr_4_screenshot_assignment.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata contentwidth="5in"
						fileref="mout/pr_4_screenshot_assignment.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>Project 4: Use the program developed in project (3)
						to solve example 5-1 of the text. Compare results with
						tables 5-3, 5-4, 5-5. Provide iteration history print
						out of your optimum soln. (25 pts) Due 12th week
						(Monday)</phrase>
				</textobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</screenshot>
		<caption>
			<para>This is a screenshot from part B of the seventh lecture at
			57:28.</para>
		</caption>
	</figure>
	<para>In example 5-1, <olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="GNVNOTED"/>
		requests that a <xi:include href="mout/pr_4_maxI.xml"/> segment
		cantilever beam be designed for minimum	material volume, as shown in
		<xref linkend="pr_4_gr_exampleBar"/> with the properties given
		in <xref linkend="pr_4_given"/>. The beam is also to have a rectangular
		cross section, as shown in
		<xref linkend="pr_4_gr_exampleCrossSection"/>.</para>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_given.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_gr_exampleBar.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_gr_exampleCrossSection.xml"/>
	<para>Obviously, the minimum volume would be zero, but that would not
		support the load within the given displacement and loading constraints.
		In order to identify all the constraints mathematically, I define
		several	expressions using linearized beam theory. As stated above, the
		equations I develop are slightly more general than those given without
		derivation in <olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="GNVNOTED"/>.</para>
	<para>I start with the results of a conservation of the moments (transverse
		to the beam) on a differentially small beam section and a conservation
		of the forces (axial to the beam) on the same section, which yield
		<xref linkend="pr_4_eqn_momentShearLoad_loading"/>. The solution to
		these equations is given in
		<xref linkend="pr_4_eqn_momentShearLoad_loading_solution"/>.</para>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_eqn_momentShearLoad_loading.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_eqn_momentShearLoad_loading_solution.xml"/>
	<para>With expressions for moment and shear force throughout the beam
		determined, it is possible to determine the deflection on a beam
		segment. Differential equations that relate moment and shear force to
		deflection come through the kinematic assumptions that the neutral axis
		of the beam bends into a curve of constant radius (an arc) and that
		strain varies linearly from the neutral axis. The material is assumed to
		be linearly elastic (by obeying Hooke's law for stress and strain),
		though Poisson effects are neglected. Conservation of force and moment
		are also required again. Combining these relations for a differential
		element in one of the beam sections gives
		<xref linkend="pr_4_eqn_displacement"/>.</para>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_eqn_displacement.xml"/>
	<para>From the differential relations given above:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The shear is constant if the load function is zero. Thus,
					the shear at the right hand end of any segment is equal to
					the shear at the left hand end.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The moment is a linear function of axial distance if the
					shear is constant.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The slope of the transverse displacement is a quadratic
					function of x. Across a segment, it increases by an amount
					proportional to	the square of the segment length. Its value
					on the right end of a segment is dependent on all the left
					end boundary conditions except the displacement.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The transverse displacement is a cubic function of x. The
					right end displacement is dependent on all the other
					boundary conditions on the left end.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	<para>The solution to <xref linkend="pr_4_eqn_displacement"/> is
		<xref linkend="pr_4_rep_displacement"/>. The undetermined coefficients
		are dealt with in <xref linkend="pr_4_eqn_c_i"/>.
		<xref linkend="pr_4_coordinate_conversion"/> shows the expressions
		required to transform the displacement solution back into global
		coordinates. With the given material properties and end load, the
		displacement is	now only a function of the segment dimensions.</para>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_rep_displacement.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_eqn_c_i.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_coordinate_conversion.xml"/>
	<para>The stresses in the beam are a functions of local bending moment,
		shear force, and beam dimensions. Under the maximum principal stress
		theory used in <olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="GNVNOTED"/>, only the
		axial stress is important, since it creates the maximum principal stress
		(in an entire segment) at the top left end of a segment, where the
		shear stress is zero. However, for ductile materials — the given
		properties seem to indicate that the bar is made of steel, which is a
		ductile material — maximum distortion energy is considered to be a more
		accurate theory for predicting failure, as stated in section 6-5 of
		<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="JSCMMED"/>.</para>
	<para>When using distortion energy theory to predict strength failures, one
		of the most important quantities is	the von	Mises stress, which depends
		on the shear and axial stress in a beam	segment. The von Mises stress
		is related to the von Mises yield condition and is defined so that its
		magnitude is the axial tension stress that would be required to create
		the same octahedral shear stress as that of the general stress state it
		represents. As with the maximum principal stress method, the critical
		section still occurs at the left end of a segment, but it is possible
		that if the shear is great enough, the critical height could be inside
		the segment instead of being on its top or bottom surface. The
		mathematical definition is given in
		<xref linkend="pr_4_vonMisesStress"/>.</para>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_vonMisesStress.xml"/>
	<para>From the discussion above, it is clear that an expression for the
		critical height is needed, which I provide in
		<xref linkend="pr_4_y_i_crit"/>.</para>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_y_i_crit.xml"/>
	<para>All of the mathematical definitions are in place so that I may give
		you <xref linkend="pr_4_constraint_identifiers"/>, along with
		<xref linkend="pr_4_objective"/>.</para>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_constraint_identifiers.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_objective.xml"/>
	<para>As stated in the introduction,
		<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="GNVNOTED"/> uses an equal segment
		length for all segments. I do the same in my optimization. With that
		assumption, the results turn out to be as follows in
		<xref linkend="pr_4_volume_table"/>,
		<xref linkend="pr_4_design_variable_table"/>, and
		<xref linkend="pr_4_constraint_values_table"/>.</para>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_volume_table.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_design_variable_table.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_constraint_values_table.xml"/>
	<para>In finishing this problem, I would like you to see two plots that
		really illustrate the stress field from my optimized solution. These are
		<xref linkend="pr_4_gr_principal_stress_trajectories"/> and
		<xref linkend="pr_4_gr_von_Mises_stress"/>.</para>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_gr_principal_stress_trajectories.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="mout/pr_4_gr_von_Mises_stress.xml"/>
	<para>I also should say that <xref linkend="pr_4_gr_exampleBar"/> is the
		result of removing the equal segment length restriction and using the
		more advanced Mathematica global optimization routines, rather than my
		local optimization routine.	The same can be said of
		<xref linkend="pr_4_gr_exampleCrossSection"/>, which actually shows the
		first cross section of <xref linkend="pr_4_gr_exampleBar"/>.</para>
	<para>Finally, the code behind the analysis in this chapter may be
		found in <olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="PR4_code"/>, while the
		complete iteration history of my ALM method	may be found in
		<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="PR4_ALM_Iteration_History"/>.</para>
</chapter>