<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<appendix xml:id="Constrained_Optimization_Methods_PR3_Appendix"
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	version="5">
	<title>Constrained Optimization Methods — Project 3</title>
	<example xml:id="pr_3_multidimensional_optimization_major_variables">
		<title>Multidimensional Optimization Major Variables</title>
		<para>Here is a list of all the major variables found within the
			Augmented Lagrange Multiplier and Variable Metric Method flow
			charts from
			<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="Calling_the_ALM_Search"/>.</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>*New</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>I have used a variable naming schere where any
					variable name that ends with New is the new value of that
					variable. This naming convention allows me to continue to
					use both the new and original values of the variable until
					I am ready to dispose of of the original.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>*Rule</term><term>*Rules</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>I have used a variable naming scheme where any
						variable name that ends with Rule is a rule for
						that variable. For instance displacementRule is a rule
						for displacement. In the Mathematica language and within
						my flowcharts, rules may be used for selective
						evaluation with the ReplaceAll operator,
						<quote>/.</quote>, shown here in quotation marks. For
						instance, <command>1 + d /. d -> 9</command>, where
						<quote>-></quote> is the operator that indicates a rule,
						would give the result of 10. Note that my flowcharts do
						not use exact Mathematica syntax because it is fairly
						involved and would require much more explanation. Also
						in my scheme, a variable name ending in Rules is a list
						of rules.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>accuracyGoal</term><term>precisionGoal</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>These two variables have the same meaning that they
						have in
						<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="Line_Search_Major_Variables"/>.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>constraints</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>This is required to be a logical And expression that
						joins constraints such as equalities or inequalities. It
						can't contain any logical disjunctions, (Or). If the
						expression is instead a list, the list is interpreted as
						an And.	Inequalities of the form x &lt; y &lt; z are
						changed to x &lt; y &amp;&amp; y &lt; z, where
						<quote>&amp;&amp;</quote> stands for a logical And. In
						the source code, after this process of flattening and
						splitting, constraints ir renamed constraintsList, but
						the flow charts only use the name constraints.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>displacement</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>displacement is the distance along searchDirection
						that the line search moves to find a new minimum.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>f</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The expression to be optimized. In the case of the
						ALM method, it is just the function to be optimized. In
						the case of the variable metric method, it could also
						include penalty terms. In the source code, this variable
						is called <quote>function</quote>.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>gradient</term><term>gradientNumeric</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>This is the list of partial derivatives of f. This is
						generated symbolically by Mathematica's command, D.
						gradientNumeric is the gradient evaluated at
						the present values of the independent variables.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>inverseHessianApprox</term><term>gradient change</term>
				<term>displacement vector</term><term>sigma</term>
				<term>tau</term><term>gamma</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>inverseHessianApprox is an approximation to the
						inverse Hessian of f that is found in the Variable
						Metric Method inner loop. The other terms listed in this
						entry just store intermediate values on the way to
						calculating a new approximation.
						The Hessian of f is the matrix of second partial
						derivatives with respect to its independent variables.
						The calculation of a new version of the inverse Hessian
						requires a lot of linear algebra. The complete formula
						is given in the source code and in section &#167; 3.3-3
						of <olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="GNVNOTED"/>.
						inverseHessianApprox is actually called
						inverseHessianApproximation in the source code.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>initialLagrangeMultiplier</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>This is the user-supplied initial value for all
						Lagrange multipliers. If it isn't specificed, the
						default is 0.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>iterations</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>This variable doesn't actually exist in the source
						code due to the functional style of the code. However,
						it is included in the flow-chart because the chart
						requires a procedural method to indicate loop flow
						control.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>lagrangeMultiplierUpdates</term>
				<term>lagrangeMultiplierUpdate</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>lagrangeMultiplierUpdates is a list of terms to add
						component-wise to the
						list of Lagrange multipliers when it is time to update
						them between iterations. The update formulas are given
						in &#167; 5-9.3 of
						<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="GNVNOTED"/>. The
						exact formula for each update is dependent on the type
						of constraint (equaltiy, less than, or greater than). In
						order to show that part of the logic, I would have to
						introduce much Mathematica syntax into the flow chart;
						so I don't.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>maxIterations</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The maximum number of iterations of the inner core of
						the method. It defaults to 100. This means there could
						be 10000 line searches (100 ALM iterations times 100
						VMM iterations per ALM iteration).</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>nSameQ</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>nSameQ is a function that tests the equality of
						numbers based on the accuracyGoal and precisionGoal,
						performing the same comparison mentioned in the ptol
						entry of
						<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="Line_Search_Major_Variables"/>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>penalties</term><term>penalty</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>penalties is a sum of penalty terms generated by the
						ALM method to add to f before handing off to the
						Variable Metric method for an unconstrained
						optimization. The formula for the penalty depends
						on the type of constraint (equality, less than, greater
						than) and is given in &#167; 5-9.3 of
						<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="GNVNOTED"/>. In order
						to show that part of the logic, I would
						have to introduce much Mathematica syntax into the flow
						chart; so I don't.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>penaltyMultiplier</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>penaltyMultiplier is a linear coefficient for all the
						(equivalent) constraint violations, which appear as
						part of the penalty terms in the unconstrained
						optimization subproblems.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>penaltyMultiplierGrowthFactor</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>This stores the multipler for the penalty multiplier.
						It defaults to the golden ratio, &#934;, from
						mathematics;
						<inlineequation><mathphrase>&#934; = growthFactor &#8773; 1.618</mathphrase></inlineequation>.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>searchDirection</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>This is the direction in which the unimodal line
						search is cast inside the kernel of the VMM search.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>solutionRules</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>For most other variables, I just define the stem of
						the variable name and let the *Rule definition, above,
						define the rest. However, this variable is used often
						enough to warrant its own description. Also, it has no
						non-Rule counterpart. solutionRules gives the present
						value of variables as the right hand sides of its rules.
						It is used to substitute the variable values into
						another expression via the ReplaceAll operator, which
						is also defined in the *Rule definition.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>variableStartRanges</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>This contains an array of independent variables and
						their inital minimum and maximum start interval
						endpoints for the ALM method.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>variableStarts</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>This contains an array of independent variables and
						their inital positions/coordinate values for the VMM.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>variables</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>These are the independent variables specified
						by the user. They don't have to be symbols; they could
						by represented by non-existent DownValues, such as 
						var[b], var[a], var[c], etc.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</example>
	<example xml:id="pr_3_appendix_Project_3_ALM_Iteration_History">
		<title>Project 3 ALM Iteration History</title>
		<para>The following two tables give the iteration or evaluation history
			of my constrained numerical optimization code for the Keane bump and
			F objectives (plus penalty functions).</para>
		<xi:include href="mout/pr_3_keane_evaluations_table.xml"/>
		<xi:include href="mout/pr_3_f_evaluations_table.xml"/>
	</example>
	<example xml:id="PR3_code">
		<?dbfo keep-together="auto"?>
		<title>Project 3 Code</title>
		<para>This is the code for the project 3 calculations.</para>
		<programlisting><xi:include href="mout/PR3.m"
			parse="text"/></programlisting>
	</example>
</appendix>