<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="HW1"
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
	version="5">
	<title>Lagrange Multipliers — Homework 1</title>
	<para><xref linkend="hw_1_screenshot"/> below shows our first homework
		assignment as given by Dr. Mohamed El-Sayed.
	</para>
	<figure xml:id="hw_1_screenshot">
		<title>Homework 1 Assignment</title>
		<screenshot>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata fileref="mout/hw_1_screenshot.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata contentwidth="5in"
						fileref="mout/hw_1_screenshot.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>1-5 Given the ellipse (X/2)^2+Y^2=4, it is required 
						to find the rectangle of greatest area which will fit 
						inside the ellipse. a. State this mathematically as a
						constrained	minimization problem. b. Analytically
						determine the optimimum	dimensions of the rectangle
						and the area. c. Draw the ellipse and the rectangle on
						the same figure.
					</phrase>
				</textobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</screenshot>
		<caption>
			<para>This is a video screen capture from the end of the first
				session.
			</para>
		</caption>
	</figure>
	<para>As <xref linkend="hw_1_screenshot"/> shows, I am to solve
		problem 1-5 of <citation>GNVNOTED</citation>. The block quotation below
		gives the problem statement in its entirety.
	</para>
	<blockquote>
		<attribution><citation>GNVNOTED</citation>, p30</attribution>
		<para><emphasis role="strong">1-5</emphasis> Given the
			ellipse <xi:include href="mout/hw_1_ellipse_inline.xml"/>, it is
			desired to find the rectangle of greatest area which
			will fit inside the ellipse.
		<orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
			<listitem>
				<para>State this mathematically as a constrained minimization
					problem. That is, set up the problem for solution using
					numerical optimization.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Analytically determine the optimum dimensions of the
					rectangle and its corresponding area.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Draw the ellipse and the rectangle on the same
					figure.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		</para>
	</blockquote>
	<para>Since the question is given in three alphabetical	parts, I respond in
		kind. I also provide my computer solution program in the
		<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="HW1_Appendix"/>.
	<orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
		<listitem>
			<para>The question requires that the problem be restated in the
				language of numerical optimization as given in the book. Using
				that language, maximization of the rectangle area is interpreted
				as the minimization of F, the negative of the area. Also, all
				optimization variables are considered to be part of one solution
				vector, separate from any physical variable naming scheme that
				may be present in the problem at hand. To differentiate between
				the	geometric variables given in the book and the variables I
				use for solving the optimization problem, I introduce the symbol
				P (for point) to indicate geometric variables and the symbol O
				to indicate optimization variables. Thus, the equation given in
				the question is recast as <xref linkend="hw_1_ellipse"/>.
				<xref linkend="hw_1_unbound_f"/> shows the geometry of the
				problem and the geometric variables (but not the optimization
				variables).
			</para>
			<xi:include href="mout/hw_1_ellipse.xml"/>
			<xi:include href="mout/hw_1_unbound_f.xml"/>
			<para>By intuition, if the ellipse circumscribes the rectangle,
				all four corners of the rectangle will lie on the ellipse. Since
				the rectangle has four points and is a two dimensional geometric
				object, eight design variables are needed. Let odd numbered
				ordinals of the design vector,
				<xi:include href="mout/hw_1_XO.xml"/>,
				designate rectangle coordinates along the 
				<xi:include href="mout/hw_1_XP.xml"/> axis. Let even
				numbered ordinals of the design vector designate rectangle
				coordinates along the <xi:include href="mout/hw_1_YP.xml"/>
				axis. The counterpart for each variable is shown in
				<xref linkend="hw_1_spacemapping"/>.
			</para>
			<xi:include href="mout/hw_1_spacemapping.xml"/>			
			<para>A rectangle's area is the magnitude of the cross product
				of the displacement vectors to the two nearest corners from
				a common corner. As stated above, F is the negative of the area
				of the rectangle, such that minimizing F maximizes the
				rectangular	area. The negative of a cross product in regular
				Cartesian space is simply the same product in reverse order.
				Choosing <xi:include href="mout/hw_1_P1.xml"/> as the location
				of the common corner and assuming the rectangular point
				designation, i in <xi:include href="mout/hw_1_Pi.xml"/>,
				increases sequentially in a counter-clockwise direction
				along the perimeter of the rectangle from that corner, the
				equation defining F is as follows in <xref
				linkend="hw_1_fmag"/>. Substituting the optimization
				variables gives the last equation in that set. Notice that
				in this definition of F, <xi:include
				href="mout/hw_1_XO5.xml"/>/<xi:include
				href="mout/hw_1_XP3.xml"/> and <xi:include
				href="mout/hw_1_XO6.xml"/>/<xi:include
				href="mout/hw_1_YP3.xml"/> do not appear.
			</para>
			<xi:include href="mout/hw_1_fmag.xml"/>
			<para>For the ellipse to circumscribe the rectangle, the equation
				of the ellipse serves an as en equality constraint between the
				<xi:include href="mout/hw_1_XP.xml"/> and
				<xi:include href="mout/hw_1_YP.xml"/> components of each point.
				This restriction yield the first four constraints on the
				optimization variables in <xref linkend="hw_1_hconstraints"/>.
				These constraints give rise to the parallelogram pictured in
				<xref linkend="hw_1_partially_constrained_f"/>.				
			</para>
			<xi:include href="mout/hw_1_partially_constrained_f.xml"/>			
			<para>More information about the geometry of the rectangle is
				required. By intuition, the orthogonality of the two vectors
				used to express the area must be guaranteed. This is
				accomplished by setting the dot product of the two vectors to
				zero in the fifth constraint. The last two constraints were
				implicit in the definition of the rectangle area as the cross
				product of two adjacent	legs of a parallelogram. The restriction
				is that both <xi:include href="mout/hw_1_XP.xml"/> and
				<xi:include href="mout/hw_1_YP.xml"/> components of
				<xi:include href="mout/hw_1_P3.xml"/> must be formed by the
				vector addition of the two displacements in the cross product.
				All seven constraints are shown in
				<xref linkend="hw_1_hconstraints"/>.
			</para>
			<xi:include href="mout/hw_1_hconstraints.xml"/>
			<para>The problem is now in the numeric optimization form
				specified by <citation>GNVNOTED</citation>. Part a of the
				problem is complete.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>This seven-constraint single-objective optimization problem
				may be solved by the method of Lagrange multipliers from 
				calculus as shown, for example, in <citation>JSCET</citation>,
				p 805. <xref linkend="hw_1_lagrangemultipliers"/> shows the
				method as it applies to this problem. The solution is a linear
				combination of the gradients of the constraints. In my
				understanding, the solution vector lies	on the hyperplane formed
				by the constraint gradients. Expanding all eight components of
				the	solution and constraint gradients gives
				<xref linkend="hw_1_lagrangeconstraints"/>.
			</para>
			<xi:include href="mout/hw_1_lagrangemultipliers.xml"/>
			<xi:include href="mout/hw_1_lagrangeconstraints.xml"/>
			<para>By combining the solutions to
				<xref linkend="hw_1_hconstraints"/> and
				<xref linkend="hw_1_hconstraints"/>, sixteen constrained
				critical states of <xref linkend="hw_1_fmag"></xref> are found.
				These states correspond to mirrors and rotations of two basic
				minimum and maximum area configurations. One basic layout forms
				a rectangle with zero area, of which there are eight possible
				configurations. The other basic layout is that of maximum area
				and minimum objective. One such solution is shown below in
				<xref linkend="hw_1_selectedsolution"/>. The objective
				function (F) minimum value is -16. The maximum area value is
				16. This answers part b of the problem.
			</para>
			<xi:include href="mout/hw_1_selectedsolution.xml"/>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>The last part, c, of the homework only requests a graph of the
				optimum solution, which I provide in
				<xref linkend="hw_1_minimum_constrained_f"/>.
			</para>
			<xi:include href="mout/hw_1_minimum_constrained_f.xml"/>
		</listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	</para>
</chapter>