<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="Variable_Metric_Unconstrained_Optimization_Methods"
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
	version="5">
	<title>Variable Metric Unconstrained Optimization Methods &#x2014; Project 2</title>
	<para>As Dr. Mohamed El-Sayed shows in
		<xref linkend="pr_2_screenshot_assignment"/>, the assignment is to solve
		<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="GNVNOTED"/> example 3-3 using the DFP
		and BFGS variable metric methods, which were developed as flow charts in
		class. I am also to provide the program code and a report.</para>
	<para>As presented in <olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="GNVNOTED"/>,
		example 3-3 is rather long. I present it here in my own words, rather
		than quoting it.  The requested code is available in
		<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="PR2_code"/>, which contains my
		application of the methods to the problem, and
		<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="Common_Source_Appendix"/>, which
		contains the variable metric method algorithm.</para>
	<figure xml:id="pr_2_screenshot_assignment">
		<title>Homework 2 Assignment</title>
		<screenshot>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata fileref="mout/pr_2_screenshot_assignment.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata contentwidth="5in" 
						fileref="mout/pr_2_screenshot_assignment.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>Project 2 (25%, 9th week) 1) Develop the DFP, BFGS
						code for multivariable unconstrained optimization
						programs using the flow chart developed in class. 2) Use
						project	(1) program to solve for the single variable
						sub-optimization problem. 3) Hand out, program, report,
						soln of the assigned problem. 4) use example 3-3 as the
						assigned problem to solve, *project due Monday 9th week
						(25%)</phrase>
				</textobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</screenshot>
		<caption>
			<para>This is a screenshot from part A of the fifth lecture at 9:57.</para>
		</caption>
	</figure>
	<para>Example 3-3 shows five masses attached to six springs in a string or
		necklace formation. The left and right ends are attached to fixed pin
		supports. The masses are under the influence of gravity. My reproduction
		of the deformed layout is presented in <xref linkend="hw_2_animation"/>.
		In my version, springs are represented with lines.
		<phrase role="animation">The animation was created by assuming each
		spring also acts as a damper. To solve the dynamic version of the
		problem, a Lagrangian formulation was used, as discussed in
		<xref linkend="Lagrangian_Mechanics_Formulation"/>.</phrase></para>
	<xi:include href="mout/hw_2_animation.xml"/>
	<para>The multidimensional variable metric method implemented for this
		assignment is the same as that presented in
		<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="hw_2_dfp_detail"/> and
		<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="hw_2_bfgs_detail"/>.</para>
	<para>Values of the problem <emphasis role="strong">constants</emphasis> are
		given in <xref linkend="hw_2_constants_by_index"/> below. I numbered the
		springs in increasing consecutive order from left to right across
		<xref linkend="hw_2_animation"/>, and that value is	reflected in the
		subscript of the stiffness, K, for each. According to
		<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="GNVNOTED"/>, the free length,
		<xi:include href="mout/hw_2_l_naught.xml"/>, of each spring is ten
		meters. I also numbered the weights, W, in increasing order from left to
		right. Points, (X, Y) pairs, occur at the each end of a spring and are
		numbered sequentially from left to right. There are a total of seven
		points, six	springs, and five weights. Note that weight 1 is at point 2,
		weight 2 is	at point 3, and so on.</para>
	<xi:include href="mout/hw_2_constants_by_index.xml"/>
	<para>Initial<phrase condition="no-animation"> optimization</phrase> values
		for the objective function and independant variables are given in
		<xref linkend="hw_2_initialValues"/>. The initial configuration
		corresponds to all points being at the same zero height datum and spaced
		<xi:include href="mout/hw_2_l_naught.xml"/> from their nearest
		neighbors, forming a horizontal line.</para>
	<xi:include href="mout/hw_2_initialValues.xml"/>
	<para>The potential energy function, PE, is given in
		<xref linkend="hw_2_potential_energy"/>. Its minimum, as derived by
		Mathematica's reference NMinimize command and by my variable metric
		methods is presented in
		<xref linkend="hw_2_method_comparison"/>. The
		table shows that both variations of my method agree with the
		reference to at least three significant figures.</para>
	<xi:include href="mout/hw_2_potential_energy.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="mout/hw_2_method_comparison.xml"/>
	<section xml:id="Lagrangian_Mechanics_Formulation" condition="animation">
		<title>Lagrangian Mechanics Formulation of
			<olink targetdoc="self" targetptr="GNVNOTED"/> Example 3-3</title>
		<para>In the book, the example only deals with the steady state
			equilibrium problem, correctly relying on the minimization of
			the potential energy to indicate the final state of the
			system. However, this student is also interested in how the
			system goes from its inital position, with all the weights
			level at zero height, to the deformed necklace shown at the end
			of <xref linkend="hw_2_animation"/>.</para>
		<para>To achieve the steady state, a method must exist for the
			system to bleed off energy. I inserted some non-conservative
			elements &#x2014; linear dampers with a coefficient, c, of 10
			Newtons for each meter per second of relative velocity between
			any two spring-connected points &#x2014; into the problem
			formulation, as mentioned above.</para>
		<para>Example 3-3 already provides the system potential energy,
			while <xref linkend="hw_2_kinetic_energy"/><note><para>The symbol g
				stands for Earth's local gravitation acceleration, nominally
				taken to be <xi:include href="mout/hw_2_gravity.xml"/></para></note>
			and	<xref linkend="hw_2_rayleigh_dissipation"/> are
			straightforward to calculate, making the Lagrangian mechanics
			formulation a natural fit.<!--good spot for a book reference--></para>
		<xi:include href="mout/hw_2_kinetic_energy.xml"/>
		<xi:include href="mout/hw_2_rayleigh_dissipation.xml"/>
		<para><xref linkend="hw_2_lagrange_equation_of_motion"/> governs
			this problem. <xi:include href="mout/hw_2_Qj_capital.xml"/>
			corresponds	to each entry in the Q vector of generalized forces. For
			this problem, Q is a zero vector.
			<xi:include href="mout/hw_2_qj_lower.xml"/>	corresponds to each
			entry in the q vector of generalized
			coordinates. For this problem, q's entries correspond to each
			ordinate of each of the	five unfixed points in this problem; thus,
			q has ten entries and there are ten second order equations of motion
			&#x2014; one for each degree of freedom of the system.</para>
		<xi:include href="mout/hw_2_lagrange_equation_of_motion.xml"/>
		<para>The ten equations are not reproduced here, because they are long
			and rather uninformative. The solution to these equations
			<emphasis>is</emphasis> available here, in the animation of
			<xref linkend="hw_2_animation"/>. Finally, once the
			vibrations die off, the Lagrange formulation yields the same
			result as the PE minimization.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>